<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A centurie of similies. By Thomas Shelton</title>
            <author>Shelton, Thomas, 1601-1650?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12102</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22403</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117258</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852473</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852473</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17797</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12102)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17797)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1007:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A centurie of similies. By Thomas Shelton</title>
                  <author>Shelton, Thomas, 1601-1650?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 62, [10] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Dawson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes index.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17797:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17797:1"/>
            <p> A CENTVRIE OF <hi>SIMILIES.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY THOMAS SHELTON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 78. 2. </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>I will open my mouth in a parable.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by <hi>Iohn Dawſon,</hi> 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17797:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17797:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Reatures inanimate, though they have motion, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, yet they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of the knowledge of what they doe, The ſea ebbs, and flowes, the ſunne ſhines, heates and moves continually: The winde goeth his circuits, the fire burnes, the trees and plants grow, yet none of them have intelligence that they doe ſo, but are all carried by a ſecret impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the firſt mover, Creatures that are brutiſh, all the knowledge they have is bounded in the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
<pb facs="tcp:17797:3"/> of ſenſuall appetite. Man, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indued with a reaſonable ſoule, with an indefatigable motion, rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth after knowledge of things, humane and divine, and is then beſt apaid, when his knowledg is at once divers wayes enriched, when ſeverall things concurre to adde to his ſtock. Beautie is delightfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a mixture of different colours; proportion is comely being a fit compoſure of different members: Muſicke is pleaſant being a harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of different ſounds.</p>
            <p>Now that man might at once both vnderſtand things that are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, (and therefore in their owne knowledge above his reach) and might alſo reape both profit and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>light God hath delivered truths in
<pb facs="tcp:17797:3"/> the old teſtament vnder types, and figures; in the new by ſimilitudes &amp; compariſons. There is nothing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in nature either in heaven or earth, but God hath made vſe of it to ſet forth the excellency of Chriſt, and the good things wee have by him. Chriſt himſelfe is compared to the <hi>ſunne,</hi> to <hi>water,</hi> to <hi>bread,</hi> to a <hi>vine,</hi> &amp;c. Grace by Chriſt, to <hi>garments,</hi> a <hi>feaſt, gold, eye-ſalve.</hi> Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to <hi>Throns, Crownes, Kingdomes,</hi> &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that together vpon the ſight, or thought of theſe things, we might be raiſed up to contemplate the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies, in and by him. And as the beſt ſo alſo the worſt things are this way conveyed to our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion. Sinne is compated to <hi>filthineſſe, vomit, rags,</hi> &amp;c. Sinners to <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:17797:4"/> 
               <hi>tigers, beares, ſerpents</hi> &amp;c. The pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of ſin to <hi>chaines, priſon,</hi> &amp;c. that by theſe ſenſible evills wee might the better conceiue of thoſe which are unutterable,</p>
            <p>And for this purpoſe I have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured theſe few ſimilies to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like view, that the reader at once might have profit with pleaſure. I intended a far greater number; but conſidering how vntowardly the left-handed world reacheth things, I thought fit to pauze a while and for the preſent only ſend a few for a taſt, &amp; as I ſee them reliſhed, I ſhall (God willing) either increaſe their number, or wiſh them in my cloſet againe.</p>
            <p>I thought it not very needfull to obſerve a method in placing them
<pb facs="tcp:17797:4"/> vnder ſeverall heads, being ſo few in number that they all require no long time to peruſe; yet thoſe that will not be at that paines may eaſe themſelves by a ſmall table annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. I have alſo to each ſimile ſet downe a text of ſcripture agreeable to the ſcope of it, by all which that thou mayſt be benefited, ſhal be the deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>THOMAS SHELTON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17797:5"/>A CENTVRIE OF SIMILIES.</head>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <head>1. <hi>Danger of ſecret ſins,</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ruine of a houſe is not vſually by the <note place="margin">Fire.</note> fire on the hearth, where the greateſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ire is, but by ſome ſmall ſparke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat lies hid in ſome corner. So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſoule of man is not ſo much
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ndangered by ſinnes that are
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:17797:6"/> knowne, and ſo may bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of: but by thoſe that are hidden and no notice taken of them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <head>2. <hi>Sin brings judgement at the laſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Piece of Match ſet to a traine of Gun-powder it <note place="margin">Gunpow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> burneth dimme a great while but blowes up all at the laſt. So a ſinner may go one ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for a time, but at length a dart will ſtrike through his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 7. 23.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="part">
            <head>3. <hi>Death of wicked men.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS a mad-man after ſleepe <note place="margin">Sleepe of mad-men.</note> is more outragious when
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17797:6"/> the malignant humour is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocted. So after death a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 46</note> man awakes with eternall horror.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="part">
            <head>4. <hi>Sin will be felt hereafter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Man that receives a wound <note place="margin">Wound.</note> in his heate, feeles it not, but when he comes to bee cold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t paines him. So the ſins where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro</hi> 13. 25.</note> Satan wounds us, wee are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſenſible of them in the heat of our paſſion, but when we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re layd in the cold earth, we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hall feele the hurt of them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="part">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:17797:7"/>
            <head>5. <hi>Why men are not offended with others ſins.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Company of priſoners that live together in a <note place="margin">Priſon.</note> Goale, they ſmell no ill ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, being accuſtomed to it. So wicked men living in the ſame ſins, they ſee no evill in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50. 18</note> the ſins of other men.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="part">
            <head>6. <hi>God mercifull by nature.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Flint yeeldeth not fire bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by force, but a ſpring ſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth <note place="margin">Spring.</note> forth water naturally. So God ſheweth not forth wrath but as provoked by ſin: but he <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mi.</hi> 7. 18.</note>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:17797:7"/> is mercifull from his owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="part">
            <head>7. <hi>Mercy of God ſupreame.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS in a City or Corpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <note place="margin">Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates.</note> men otherwiſe equal are choſen to beare rule for a time. So though all Gods at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes be equall: yet mercy is
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145. 9.</note> that which cheifly reigneth in Chriſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="part">
            <head>8. <hi>How to inſtruct the weake.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Bottle or veſſell with a <note place="margin">Bottle.</note> narrow mouth, liquor muſt be poured into it ſoftly, or elſe more is ſpilt then filled. So <note place="margin">Jſa. 28. 10.</note> thoſe of weaker capacities muſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17797:8"/> be taught by degrees, and not ſurcharged.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="part">
            <head>9. <hi>The uſe of promiſes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHen Chirurgions cut off a leg or an arme, they uſe to give the Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſtrong water aforehand to <note place="margin">Strong water.</note> comfort him. So when a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is approaching we ſhould fortifie our ſelves with Gods <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 31. 6.</note> promiſes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="part">
            <head>10. <hi>Cauſe of lifes ſhortneſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Veſſell of wine kept for a mans owne vſe or hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <note place="margin">Wine.</note> friends may laſt a good whil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being moderately dranke of, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:17797:8"/> if thoſe come that are ſtrong to drinke ſtrong drinke, that may be ſpent in a day, which would have laſted a moneth. So mans life which otherwiſe with
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90. 9.</note> temperance, and care might be ſpun out to 30. 40. 50. or 60. yeares, if God let in great drin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, as burning feaver, plague, &amp;c. it is ſpent on a ſudden.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="part">
            <head>11. <hi>Curſe of covetous men.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS a womans breaſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged with milke, if it <note place="margin">Milke.</note> be not drawne forth, not onely paines the woman, but putrifies and becomes unwholſome. So a man to whom God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 5. 2.</note> ability, that improves it not for the good of others, it turnes to his owne hurt and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="part">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:17797:9"/>
            <head>12. <hi>How to uſe outward bleſsings.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Man that walkes by a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, if hee follow the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <note place="margin">River.</note> againſt the ſtreame it will at length lead him to the ſpring from whence it iſſueth, but if he goe along with the ſtreame it will bring him to the ſalt O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean. So he that well improo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth outward bleſſings, they will lead him to God the ſweet <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Job.</hi> 29. 6.</note> fountaine of them: but other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the abuſe of them will bring him to the <hi>Mare mortuum</hi> of perdition.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="part">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:17797:9"/>
            <head>13. <hi>Argument of mans weakeneſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IF a man come by a houſe that is ſhored up and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propped <note place="margin">Houſe.</note> on every ſide, he will conclude certainely that houſe is weake of it ſelfe that needeth ſuch ſtayes. So when God hath vnderpropped, and ſupported vs with ſo many helpes, his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 116.</note> word, ſacraments, promiſes, and oath &amp;c. it is an argument of weakeneſſe that we cannot ſtand without them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="part">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:17797:10"/>
            <head>14. <hi>Defect of reaſon.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Sunne by his light <note place="margin">Sunne.</note> ſhewes us all things that are beneath him ſelfe, but hideth thoſe that are aboue. So the light of naturall reaſon ſhewes
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14.</note> vs thoſe things that are beneath, that are ſenſible, but hinders from thoſe above that are ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="part">
            <head>15. <hi>Death of wicked men vntimely.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AN apple though it hang <note place="margin">Apple.</note> long on the tree, yet if it be gathered before it be ripe it is pluckt untimely. So a wicked
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17797:10"/> man though he live a long time, yet his death is untimely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<note place="margin">Iſay 66 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> he is taken away before he is fitted for death.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="part">
            <head>16. <hi>Contentment of the humble.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe ſheepe can live upon <note place="margin">Sheepe.</note> the bare mountains where the fat Oxe would be ſtarved. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. 13.</note> So a humble heart is content with a meane condition, which a proud ſpirit would murmure at.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="part">
            <head>17. <hi>Abundance of outward things a hindrance</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Man that is to travell, a great burden or pack at his <note place="margin">Packe.</note>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:17797:11"/> backe hinders his journey. So worldly men hinder their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hab.</hi> 2. 6.</note> to heaven by loading themſelves with thicke clay.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="part">
            <head>18. <hi>Another.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ONe ſtaffe in a mans hand <note place="margin">Staffe.</note> may helpe him in his journey, but a bundle of ſtaues would be troubleſome. So a competencie may helpe in the way to heaven; whereas abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. 10</note> may be hurtfull.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="part">
            <head>19. <hi>Another.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>PRoſperitie, and abundance <note place="margin">Long Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> are like long garments to a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17797:11"/> man that walkes, they will trip up his heeles if he take not heed.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 4. 29.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="part">
            <head>(20) <hi>Another.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS a weake braine cannot <note place="margin">Strong drinke.</note> beare ſtrong waters but is intoxicated with it. So by reaſon of our weakenes proſperity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hab.</hi> 2. 5.</note> a ſnare to us.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="part">
            <head>21. <hi>Wicked men enioy plentie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AN hoſt may give better en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment <note place="margin">Hoſt.</note> to a ſtranger that comes to his houſe for a night, then to his own child: but <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 17. 14</note> yet he keeps his inheritance for his child. So in this world God may give more abundance of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:17797:12"/> outward things to his enemies but he keepes the inheritance of
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 4.</note> heaven for his children.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="part">
            <head>22 <hi>Why good mens lives are prolon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Rivers of themſelves would run the ſtraiteſt and <note place="margin">River.</note> directeſt way to the ſea, but God hath ſet mountaines, and hills in the way, that by winding and going further about, they might the more enrich the earth. So a Chriſtian having once taſted of Gods love deſires to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.,</hi> 1. 13 24</note> and to be with Chriſt; but God prolongs his life to do good to others.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="part">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:17797:12"/>
            <head>23. <hi>Rewards and puniſhments.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHen the hands of <hi>Moſes</hi> were feeble <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aaron</hi> &amp; <hi>Hur.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur</hi> ſupported them, that they might not fall. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards and puniſhments are the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 23. 41.</note> two hands that ſupport good lawes that otherwiſe would fall to the ground.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="part">
            <head>24. <hi>A Chriſtians carriage in all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS men that are carried in a boate, they ſet themſelves <note place="margin">Boate.</note> ſome on one ſide, and ſome on the other to poize the boate
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17797:13"/> even. So a chriſtian when he is ready to bee overturned with proſperity ſhould meditate on that which may humble him, and when hee is ready to ſinke <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 9.</note> in affliction to thinke on that which may raiſe him up, that his carriage may be equall.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="25" type="part">
            <head>25 <hi>Deformitie of ſin.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Looking glaſſe when it is whole, it repreſenteth, but <note place="margin">Broken looking glaſſe.</note> one face to him that lookes in it, but being broken, there appears as many faces as there are pei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. So ſin being looked on in generall, there is ſome deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in it, being a body of death; but being broken in peices by ſerious conſideration, there is the Image of the Devill in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry paricular ſin.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="26" type="part">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:17797:13"/>
            <head>26 <hi>Wicked men feare onely puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Dog though he have an <note place="margin">Dogge.</note> appetite to a diſh of meat, dares not meddle with it ſo long as one ſtands over him <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 24.</note> with a ſtaffe. So a wicked man ſometimes abſtaines from ſinne, but it is onely for feare of Gods judgements.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="27" type="part">
            <head>27. <hi>Infirmities in the Saints.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS the beſt Gold goes cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant <note place="margin">Gold.</note> with the graines of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance: So the Saints are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 14.</note> with God notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their infirmities.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="28" type="part">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:17797:14"/>
            <head>28. <hi>The nature of ſinne.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SInne is like to Misſle-toe <note place="margin">Misſle-toe.</note> which commonly groweth in fruit trees, yet hath no root of its owne. So ſin hath no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it ſelfe: yet is found on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude</hi> 5. 6.</note> in the moſt excellent crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, men and Angels.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="29" type="part">
            <head>29. <hi>God our ſtrength.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Nurſe ſometimes lets her child have a fall to let it <note place="margin">Nurſe.</note> know that it cannot ſtand by any ſtrength of its owne. So God lets his children fall into ſin that they may know, they <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 20. 6.</note> are no longer ſafe than they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:17797:14"/> ſtand by his ſtrength, and clapſe about him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="30" type="part">
            <head>30. <hi>Fals of Gods Children.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>GOd ſometimes ſuffers his <note place="margin">Fall.</note> children to fall that they may grow in the roote of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, humility. As the vertue of a plant is ſometimes in the fruit, as in Summer: ſometimes in <note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 22. 19.</note> the budas in the Spring: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in the roote, as in winter, &amp; commonly the ſharpeſt win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter makes the fruitfulleſt ſpring.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="31" type="part">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:17797:15"/>
            <head>31. <hi>Growth after falls.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS after a fit of ſickneſſe the <note place="margin">Sickneſſe.</note> body uſually ſhootes up more: ſo a Chriſtian after the ſight of ſome ſin hee hath fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam,</hi> 24. 10.</note> into, growes ſtronger in grace.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="32" type="part">
            <head>32 <hi>Strength from Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS the ayre is darke when the Sun is ſet though the <note place="margin">Ayre.</note> ſtarres ſhine: ſo though a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian have a diſpoſition to good, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> 15. 5.</note> if Chriſt ſhine not on him, in the doing of every particular act, he is unable to doe it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="33" type="part">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:17797:15"/>
            <head>33. <hi>Vncertaintie of riches.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Man ſeeing a flock of birds <note place="margin">Birds.</note> ſitting on his ground, can make himſelfe no promiſe of taking them: ſo though a man <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4. 8.</note> be poſſeſſed of riches, he may ſo one be deprived of them: for riches have wings, &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="34" type="part">
            <head>34. <hi>Vnprofitable knowledge.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe knowledge of every man but a Chriſtian is like <note place="margin">Beggar.</note> the knowledg of a beggar, who knoweth the roade from place <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 15. 2.</note> to place, but hath no ſetled home of his owne.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="35" type="part">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:17797:16"/>
            <head>35. <hi>Difference of men after death.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe hawke flies high, and is much made of being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live, <note place="margin">Hawke &amp; hen.</note> but being dead is good for nothing but the dunghill. The hen ſcrapes in the duſt when ſhe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 14. 32</note> is alive, but being dead is brought as a choiſe diſh to her maſters table. So wicked men proſper, and good men are aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in this life: but being dead the one is caſt into the dungeon the other aduanced to the pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="36" type="part">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:17797:16"/>
            <head>36. <hi>A Chriſtians ayme.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS waters conveyed in <note place="margin">Water.</note> pipes will riſe as high as the ſpring from whence they <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 19.</note> iſſue: ſo the ſoule of a Chriſtian being touched from heaven, it will not reſt till it riſe thither a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="37" type="part">
            <head>37. <hi>Falſe friends.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MAny men that pretend <note place="margin">Shaddow,</note> friendſhip they are like the ſhaddow of the bodie, they follow a man while the ſun of proſperitie ſhines: but if a cloud
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jſa.</hi> 30. 2.</note> of adverſity hide that ſun, thoſe ſhadowes are gone.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="38" type="part">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:17797:17"/>
            <head>38. <hi>Outward things variable</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS the ſhadow that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <note place="margin">Shaddow.</note> the body it is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times longer, ſomtimes ſhorter, but the body ſtill the ſame, ſo <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 12.</note> the honor and credit and wealth of a Chriſtian may bee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times leſſe ſometimes more, but the body of grace is the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="39" type="part">
            <head>39. <hi>Different diſpoſitions.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe fire that is made of <note place="margin">Greene wood. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 19.</note> greene wood muſt have much blowing, but a fire made of charcoale is ſoone kindled: ſo the heart of a carnall man receives not holy impreſſions
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:17797:17"/> without much adoe, but the heart of a Chriſtian, like char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coale having beene formerly kindled is apt to take fire a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="40" type="part">
            <head>40. <hi>Outward blesſings how diſpoſed.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS the Almoner of a King, <note place="margin">Almes.</note> or great man caſts his almes among a company of beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars and one or two many times <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. 9.</note> carrie all from the reſt. So theſe outward blesſings are promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly beſtowed, and ſome carry away all, and leave the reſt deſtitute.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="41" type="part">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:17797:18"/>
            <head>41. <hi>Benefit of afflictions.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS water caſt upon the ſmiths <note place="margin">Smiths water,</note> coales make them burne hotter, and brighter: ſo the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions of Gods children in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 119. 71</note> the luſtre of their graces.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="42" type="part">
            <head>42. <hi>How to underſtand Scriptures,</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS in tuning of a Lute, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Lute.</note> inſtrument, the ſtriking upon one or two ſtrings help to tune the reſt: ſo comparing one ſcripture with another is a help <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 13.</note> to underſtand them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="43" type="part">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:17797:18"/>
            <head>43. <hi>Reward of ſinceritie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Phyſitian doth not looſe <note place="margin">Phiſitian.</note> his fee though the patient miſcarrie and die. So thoſe that are ſincere hearted in the <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> worke of the Lord ſhall not looſe their reward, though the ſucceſſe be not anſwerable to their paines.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="44" type="part">
            <head>44. <hi>Diſcoverie of Gods love.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe rivers a long time run <note place="margin">Rivers.</note> under ground till at the laſt they breake forth into ſtreames, ſo Gods love in ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and redemption it is
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 31. 18</note> concealed from a man till it
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17797:19"/> breake forth in his regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and effectuall calling.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="45" type="part">
            <head>45. <hi>Way to thankfulneſſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Traytor, though he have <note place="margin">Traytor.</note> the libertie of the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to walke in, and proviſion of meat and drinke and all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries, yet he takes little plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32. 2.</note> in them becauſe his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is not pardoned, but hee expects daily to be drawn forth to execution. So a man that hath all the comforts of this life, if he want aſſurance of the pardon of his ſins, and of Gods love, he cannot bee truly thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for what he enjoyeth.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="46" type="part">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:17797:19"/>
            <head>46. <hi>How ſinners are brought to Chriſt</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Rebell, ſo long as the Hue and crie purſues him, hee <note place="margin">Hue and crie.</note> runs away and hides himſelfe; but when proclamation of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don comes forth hee comes in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 130. 4</note> and ſubmits himſelfe. So the denunciation of Gods Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments affright men that they run from God, but when par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and mercy is offred, it makes them ſubmit to Chriſt as their King.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="47" type="part">
            <head>47 <hi>Infirmities to be borne with.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Member that is diſtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <note place="margin">Member.</note> or out of joynt, is not preſently to be cut off, but <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. 23.</note>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:17797:20"/> vſed tenderly and ſet in joyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> again, ſo thoſe that are froward and pettiſh, and paſſionate, are not to bee excluded, but redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to a better temper.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="48" type="part">
            <head>(48) <hi>Gods purpoſe effected.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe wheeles in a watch, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> clock, goe contrary one to <note place="margin">Wheels of a watch.</note> another, ſome one way, ſome another, yet all ſerve the intent of the workman, to ſhew the time, or to make the clocke to ſtrike. So in the world men <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 46. 10.</note> take contrary courſes, there are good men that goe one way, and wicked men another; but all in concluſion ſerue to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the purpoſe of the great workeman God himſelfe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="49" type="part">
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:17797:20"/>
            <head>49. <hi>Difference of carnal &amp; holy men.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AN Organ or winde inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment maketh no muſicke <note place="margin">Organ.</note> till firſt there be breath put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it; but a ſtringed inſtrument yeeldeth muſicke with a touch: A carnall man being dead muſt <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 12. 2.</note> have a new life breathed into him before he can walke holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but a child of God doth good upon a touch, upon the leaſt occaſion.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="50" type="part">
            <head>50. <hi>End of perſecutors.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Shepheard ſets his dogge <note place="margin">Shepheard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> upon the ſheepe to bring them in, and then hee rates the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:17797:21"/> dogge, ſo God ſuffers evill men to moleſt his children that they
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21. 20.</note> may cleaue cloſer to him, and then hee puniſheth thoſe that troubled them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="51" type="part">
            <head>51. <hi>Way to humilitie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHen Bees begin to ſwarme the caſting <note place="margin">Bees.</note> of duſt upon them allaieth them: So when proud thoughts ariſe, the conſideration of mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12. 7</note> that wee muſt lye in the duſt will aſſwagethem.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="52" type="part">
            <head>52. <hi>Wickedneſſe diſcovered.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Snake while ſhe is living winds and turnes every <note place="margin">Snake.</note>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:17797:21"/> way, but being dead is laid out ſtraight at length: ſo wicked ſubtile men have many ſhifts and deviſes while they live, but <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. 8.</note> when they die, all is diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and laid open.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="53" type="part">
            <head>53. <hi>Difference of hypocrites and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Peece of metall that is but <note place="margin">Gilt.</note> gilt, the gilt weares off, and it is worſe &amp; worſe: but that which is maſſie gold weares brighter, and brighter. An hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite hath a gilded outſide, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 10. 20.</note> which in time weares off, and he is diſcovered, but a true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, though his outſide may ſeem ruſtie, is pure Gold within.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="54" type="part">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:17797:22"/>
            <head>54. <hi>Experience beyond knowledge.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Phiſitian knowes not the <note place="margin">Patient.</note> paine of the diſeaſe ſo well as his patient, though his learning be greater: ſo experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 19.</note> Chriſtians know the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of God better than lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men that want experience.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="55" type="part">
            <head>55. <hi>Faith and Love.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS in making of a circle, one point of the compaſſe is <note place="margin">Compaſſes</note> fixed in the middle, the other is mooved about to make the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 11.</note> Faith is as the one point of the compaſſe that is fixed on
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:17797:22"/> Chriſt, and love the other point that goeth about and doeth the worke.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="56" type="part">
            <head>56. <hi>Benefit of Conſideration.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS duſt that being ſcattered <note place="margin">Broome.</note> over the houſe, ſeemeth little, but being ſwept toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther becomes a heape: So the ſins wee have committed being looked on with a careleſſe eye, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 38. 4.</note> appeare to be no great matters, by ſerious conſideration they prove an vnſupportable bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="57" type="part">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:17797:23"/>
            <head>57. <hi>Cauſe of Trouble.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS a cloth that ſeemeth dry <note place="margin">Cloth.</note> being held to the fire will be moiſt and ſmoake, the moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture being in the cloath not in the fire. So when men come to
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 42. 6.</note> Gods ordinances they are ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times troubled, the cauſe is not in Gods ordinance but from corruption in them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="58" type="part">
            <head>58. <hi>Why God aflicts his Children.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS a Chyrurgion deſires to <note place="margin">Chirurgion</note> take way nothing but the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, but ſomtimes it is feſtred <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 49. 10.</note> ſo in the member, that he is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:17797:23"/> to cut off the member with it: So God intends we ſhould part with nothing but ſin: but it is ſo rivetted in us that hee is forced to take away other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments that wee may part with our ſins.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="59" type="part">
            <head>59. <hi>Progreſſe in our ſpirituall Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Man that traivaileth, thoſe <note place="margin">Traveller.</note> Townes and places that he hath paſſed ſeeme leſſe and leſſe, and thoſe to which hee is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching, to appeare greater <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 27.</note> and greater. So a Chriſtian in his journey to heaven the things of the world that he hath left behind, they appeare leſſer and leſſer; but the things of heaven greater and greater.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="60" type="part">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:17797:24"/>
            <head>60. <hi>Obiect of the ſoule.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Cypher ſtands for nothing <note place="margin">Cipher.</note> by it ſelfe, but by other fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures placed before it, it makes a number. So the ſoule of man, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 11.</note> like a Cypher is valued by that which it ſets before it whether it be God or the world.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="61" type="part">
            <head>61. <hi>Efficacie of Gods love.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Sunne caſts light and <note place="margin">Burning glaſſe.</note> heate upon all the world in his generall courſe: but his beames being concenterate in <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1. 18.</note> a burning glaſſe, it ſets fire u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the obiect. So God in the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:17797:24"/> creation looked upon all his workes with a generall love, but the beames of his love to his elect, ſhining through Chriſt inflames their hearts.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="62" type="part">
            <head>62. <hi>Civill men diſcovered.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe glow-worme appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth <note place="margin">Glow-worme.</note> bright in the night, but is not ſeene in the day time. So a civill Man is ſome bodie in darke times among men of darke judgements: but ſhall be <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. 30</note> nothing when the day of God ſhall trie him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="63" type="part">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:17797:25"/>
            <head>63. <hi>Meanes effectuall by the Spirit,</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS the Arteries goe along <note place="margin">Arteries.</note> with the veines, without which the blood would bee a dead, loathſome thing; ſo the ſpirit of God muſt goe along
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. 18.</note> with his ordinances and means or elſe they can effect nothing.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="64" type="part">
            <head>64. <hi>How to vſe good meanes</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS the Marriner that guides <note place="margin">Marriner.</note> the ſhip, at the ſame time hath his hand upon the rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and his eye on the ſtarre: ſo <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. 25.</note> we ſhould be dilgent in the uſe of means but look up to heaven for a bleſſing.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="65" type="part">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:17797:25"/>
            <head>65 <hi>Nature of worldly things.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS a man that drinketh ſalt <note place="margin">Salt water.</note> water it quencheth not his thirſt but increaſeth it, ſo the things of this life being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed, they ſatisfie not the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5. 10</note> of men but enlarge them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="66" type="part">
            <head>66. <hi>Loſt labour,</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS a bad ſwimmer may <note place="margin">Swimmer.</note> reach forth his hand to ſave another, and drowne him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: ſo a man by his parts and <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 27.</note> and gifts may do good to others and himſelf be a caſt-away.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="67" type="part">
            <head>67. <hi>God immutable.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS the ſun lookes red ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <note place="margin">Sun.</note> by reaſon of vapours
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:17797:26"/> and miſts, but in it ſelfe is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes alike: So God in himſelf is vnchangeable, though he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 29.</note> red to vs in anger by the aſsending of our ſins.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="68" type="part">
            <head>68. <hi>To ſerve God in ſerving men.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS a Man that hath a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <note place="margin">Servant.</note> ſick, and ſets another ſeruant to attend him, he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies him with thoſe things he calls for, but it is by vertue of his maſters command. So in our places though the duties wee doe bee to men yet wee muſt
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 22.</note> have an eye to the command of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="69" type="part">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:17797:26"/>
            <head>69. <hi>Not to hoord up for our ſelves.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe vapours that the Sun <note place="margin">Vapour.</note> exhaleth from the ſea are ſent downe againe to moyſten the earth. So the good things <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 7. 8.</note> that God beſtoweth on us, ſhould be diſpenſed to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of others.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="70" type="part">
            <head>70. <hi>Cure of immoderate griefe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS Phiſitians vſe, when men <note place="margin">Bleeding.</note> bleed exceſſively to open a veine, in another palce, and ſo <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 10.</note> ſtanch exceſsive bleeding: ſo when we grieve immoderately for the loſſe of outward things wee
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:17797:27"/> turne our griefe upon our ſins.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="71" type="part">
            <head>71. <hi>Care in Gods ordinances.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THough a ſcholler may be <note place="margin">Scholler.</note> playing when his Maſter walks up and down the ſchoole, yet he will bee carefull and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous when he is ſaying his leſſon: ſo though perhaps we be more <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 2.</note> remiſſe in our ordinarie vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet we ſhould have a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all eye to God, when we are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him in his ordinances.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="72" type="part">
            <head>72. <hi>How to looke on tranſcient thing.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IF a man ſtand and obſerve <note place="margin">Diall.</note> the hand of a dyall he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:17797:27"/> perceive it moove, but if he come an houre or two after, he ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l ſee that it hath mooved and that ſo much time is paſt. So if we looke on the things of the world in their paſſing wee <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 31.</note> ſhall ſee no great alteration, but if wee ſee them paſt by the eye of faith wee will neglect them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="73" type="part">
            <head>73. <hi>Flight of faith.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Pigeon having her eyes put out flyeth directly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: <note place="margin">Pigeon.</note> ſo the eye of reaſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhut faith aſcends more di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 27.</note> to divine things.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="74" type="part">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:17797:28"/>
            <head>74. <hi>Grace ſanctifieth all things.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS meat may be wholſome of it ſelfe, yet ſalt makes <note place="margin">Salt.</note> it more ſavorie: So though out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward benefits be good in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, yet it is grace that makes
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim,</hi> 5. 4.</note> them bleſſings to vs.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="75" type="part">
            <head>75 <hi>Finall obduration.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Tree after it is cut down <note place="margin">Tree.</note> may lie in the yard under the raine a long time before it be caſt into the fire. So after <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4. 17.</note> God hath forſaken a man hee may continue a long time under the meanes of grace before hee be caſt into hell fire.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="76" type="part">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:17797:28"/>
            <head>76. <hi>Defect of worldly things.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is with the things of the <note place="margin">Ducks.</note> world and the ſoule as with a hen that hatcheth ducks: the duckes after a while goe into the water, the hen may hover
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 7</note> about the brinke but cannot follow them. So the ſoule af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a while taketh her flight in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another world, and leaves theſe earthly things behind on the ſhore.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="77" type="part">
            <head>77. <hi>Faith and doubting conſiſtent.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS the Marriners needle, <note place="margin">Marriners needle.</note> though it bee truly tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched it fixeth not preſently to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:17797:29"/> the North-pole but trembles and ſhakes a while, and then is fixed: So faith may be true, and <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor</hi> 15. 58</note> yet at the firſt weake and full of trepidation and wavering.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="78" type="part">
            <head>78. <hi>Hypocrites behaviour.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS diſcontented louers upon <note place="margin">Love-tokens.</note> the leaſt diſtaſt ſend for all their love tokens back and will goe on no further. So when hipocrites are croſſed in their aymes, they repent of the good <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>al.</hi> 1. 13.</note> duties they have done, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt from Gods ſervice, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the world.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="79" type="part">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:17797:29"/>
            <head>79. <hi>Another</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS a Curre dog when his <note place="margin">Dogge.</note> maſter beats him will either flie in his face, or run from him So an hipocrite when God pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb,</hi> 3. 12.</note> him, either murmurs a-againſt him, or forſakes his ſervice.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="80" type="part">
            <head>80. <hi>The force of Cuſtome.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>CHildren at the firſt ſight of a vizor are affrighted <note place="margin">Vizor.</note> with it, but after a while they care not for it. So men that were ſometimes fearefull of
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 5. 14.</note> death: by the frequent exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of mortalitie, they grow
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:17797:30"/> careleſſe, and feareleſſe of it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="81" type="part">
            <head>81. <hi>Different carriage in an evill man.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HOrſes, and ſuch wild <note place="margin">Ferry-boat.</note> creatures, being in a Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie-boate on the water, ſtand ſtill and are quiet, but being once out of it, reſume their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer wildneſſe. So thoſe that are <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 24 2.</note> brought up in good families are many times conformable, but being once at libertie run into exceſſe of riot.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="82" type="part">
            <head>82. <hi>Concealed griefe double.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AN Oven being ſtopped when the fire is in it, it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth <note place="margin">Oven.</note> the heate: So when
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:17797:30"/> men conceale their doubts and feares, and troubles from others
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4. 9.</note> it doubleth their griefe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="83" type="part">
            <head>83. <hi>How to know wee belong to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT was wont to bee a tryall <note place="margin">Venemous creatures.</note> whether Land belonged to England or <hi>Ireland,</hi> by putting toads, and ſnakes, and other venemous creatures into it; and <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 21</note> if they lived there it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded it belonged to <hi>England;</hi> if they died; to <hi>Ireland.</hi> So if venemous luſts live in us, wee belong to hell; if they die by mortification, to heaven.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="84" type="part">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:17797:31"/>
            <head>84. <hi>The older the world the worſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS a ſinke, the further it <note place="margin">Sinck.</note> runs, the more ſoile it ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers: ſo the world the older it growes the worſe it is: the ſins <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 1.</note> of all former times meeting to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the latter.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="85" type="part">
            <head>85. <hi>Chriſtian conſtancie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS the Kine of the <hi>Bethſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> that carried the <note place="margin">Kine.</note> Arke, though they lowed after calves, yet they went right on <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 37.</note> theirway. So a Chriſtian though his heart may linger after tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall things, yet he keepes on
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:17797:31"/> in his courſe of Chriſtianity.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="86" type="part">
            <head>86. <hi>How to regard our owne praiers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>CHildren ſhoote arrowes <note place="margin">Arrowes.</note> on purpoſe to looſe them and never looke after them, but men when they ſhoot goe after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir arrowes to ſee how neere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he marke they light. So wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 88. 1.</note> men when they have made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir prayers have no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of them; but Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren looke after their prayers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd obſerve how God anſwers.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="87" type="part">
            <head>87. <hi>Efficacie of the Spirit.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS in a Cordiall potion, it is not the water or the beere <note place="margin">Drug.</note>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:17797:32"/> but the herbe or drug convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it that works the cure. So the miniſterie of the word alone <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 12</note> cannot worke upon the heart, but the ſpirit of God accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the ordinance.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="88" type="part">
            <head>88. <hi>Gods aime in afflictions.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Phiſitian gives a bit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter potion which ſome <note place="margin">Potion.</note> times makes the patient ſicke then the diſeaſe it ſelfe, but hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> end is to reſtore him to healt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by it: So the afflictions of God <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 11.</note> children ſeeme bitter potions but God aymes at the health o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> their ſoules in it.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="89" type="part">
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:17797:32"/>
            <head>89. <hi>Gods time the beſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe Phyſitian turnes the glaſſe, and reſolves the <note place="margin">Mour-glaſs.</note> phiſicke ſhall worke ſo long, the patient deſires eaſe, and cries <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 31. 15</note> out he is tormented, but the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knowes the fitteſt time. So Gods children crie out in affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, <hi>How long Lord:</hi> but the Lord knoweth the beſt time to releaſe them.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="90" type="part">
            <head>90 <hi>Corruption diſcovered.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Man that ſtirreth with a <note place="margin">Puddle.</note> ſtaffe in a veſſell or ſpring of faire water, though the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter be ſtirred it continueth ſtill <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iam.</hi> 1. 13. 14.</note>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:17797:33"/> in its cleareneſſe, but ſtirring in a puddle or finck it is preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lymuddy and offenſive. So when men provoked by others, are tranſported by their paſſions, the cauſe is not from the provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of others, but from the corruption in themſelves.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="91" type="part">
            <head>91. <hi>Hypocrite vncaſed.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHen people goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad <note place="margin">Garments.</note> they put on their gay apparell, but when they goe to bed they ſtrip them off. So an hipocrite in his life <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 14</note> may put on the garments of a faire profeſſion, but when hee comes to lie downe in the bed of death ſhall he be ſtripped of all and left naked.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="92" type="part">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:17797:33"/>
            <head>92. <hi>How to reproove great men,</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MEn that plough hilly <note place="margin">Plowing.</note> ground they goe not directly vp and downe, but ſide waies: ſo thoſe that are to tell <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12. 1</note> great men of their faults, muſt goe about as we ſee <hi>Nathan</hi> did with <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="93" type="part">
            <head>93. <hi>The wickedeſt men may be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS the earth that beareth <note place="margin">Weeds.</note> the ſtrongeſt weedes, it hath much heate in it, and <note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:17797:34"/> if it were tilled and manured it would beare good corne. So thoſe that are vileſt in their courſes, when they are once converted become moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent inſtruments of his glory.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="94" type="part">
            <head>94. <hi>To keepe in Gods wayes</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IF a man in the Kings high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <note place="margin">Kings highway.</note> be robbed in the day-time, it is recoverable from the Country, but if hee travaile at vnſeaſonable times, it is at his owne perill. So if a man keepe in Gods wayes, he hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 91. 11</note> to guard, and protect him, but if he ſtray out from them, he expoſeth himſelfe to danger.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="95" type="part">
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:17797:34"/>
            <head>95. <hi>Delayed iudgements heavie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS a man that ſhooteth in a <note place="margin">Shooting.</note> bow the further he draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the arrow backe the faſter and further it flieth: ſo though <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 48. 49. 50.</note> God many times delay his judgements, yet the ſeverity of them recompenceth his forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="96" type="part">
            <head>96. <hi>Another.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe raine it is long bottle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Raine.</note> in the clouds, but at the length it falls downe ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily in ſhowers: ſo God is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. 1.</note> long in providing his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, but at the laſt they are
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:17797:35"/> ſhowred downe ſuddenly.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="97" type="part">
            <head>97. <hi>Long prayers ſometimes dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IF a man ſhoot at a But or a ſhort marke the arrow flieth <note place="margin">Butt.</note> point blanke, and with great force: but if he ſhoot at a long marke though it go forth ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it flags, and falls at length. <note place="margin">Mat. 6. 7.</note> So the fervencie of ſpirit in prayer is ſometimes much aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ere a long prayer be ended.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="98" type="part">
            <head>98. <hi>Difference of knowledge in God and in man.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN a ſheete almanack, a man <note place="margin">Almanack</note> at one view may ſee all
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:17797:35"/> the moneths in the yeare, both paſt, and to come, but in a book almanack, as he turneth to one <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139. 2. 6.</note> ſo he turneth from another, and can looke but on the preſent. So the knowledge of God at one inſtant looketh to things, paſt, preſent and future: but the knowledge of man one-to a few things, paſt, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and that ſucceſſively.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="99" type="part">
            <head>99. <hi>Ceſſation of miracles.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS a gardiner, when he firſt <note place="margin">Tree.</note> planteth a tree, hee digs the earth, and is carefull to wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it evening and morning, but after the tree hath taken roote, he leaves it to the common in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of the heavens, ſo in the firſt preaching of the Goſpell it was neceſſarie that the gift of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:17797:36"/> miracles ſhould goe along with the gift of preaching; the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</note> then being Idolaters and vnbeleevers that never heard of Chriſt; but now the Goſpell is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. de Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit, dei. lib.</hi> 22. <hi>Cap.</hi> 8.</note> planted and ſtabliſhed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leived miracles are ſuperfluous.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="100" type="part">
            <head>100. <hi>Reward of Atheiſme.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IN the ſummer a man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <note place="margin">Breath.</note> ſee his owne breath. which in winter, he can eaſily diſcerne, So he that will not in the ſummer of this life beleeve
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 6.</note> that there is a God ſhall feel it to his eternall torment in the winter of hell.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17797:36"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17797:37"/>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:17797:37"/>
            <head>The Names of the things from whence the Similies are taken.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>FIre.</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gunpowder.</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sleepe.</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Wound.</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Priſon.</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Spring.</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Magiſtrates.</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Bottle.</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Strong water</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Wine.</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Milke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>River.</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Houſe.</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sun.</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Apples.</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sheepe.</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Packe.</cell>
                     <cell>17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Staffe.</cell>
                     <cell>18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Long Garment:</cell>
                     <cell>19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Strong drinke.</cell>
                     <cell>20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hoſt.</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>River.</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Aaron</hi> and <hi>Hur.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Boate.</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Looking-glaſſe.</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Dog.</cell>
                     <cell>26</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gold.</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Misſletoe,</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Nurſe,</cell>
                     <cell>29</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Fall.</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sickneſſe.</cell>
                     <cell>31</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Aire.</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Birds.</cell>
                     <cell>33</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Beggar.</cell>
                     <cell>34</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hawke and hen.</cell>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Water.</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Shaddow.</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Shadow.</cell>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Greene wood,</cell>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Almes.</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Smithes water.</cell>
                     <cell>41</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Lute.</cell>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Phyſitian.</cell>
                     <cell>43</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Rivers.</cell>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Traitor.</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Hue and crie.</cell>
                     <cell>46</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Member.</cell>
                     <cell>47</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Watch-wheeles.</cell>
                     <cell>48</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Organ.</cell>
                     <cell>49</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Shepheards dog.</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Bees.</cell>
                     <cell>51</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Snake.</cell>
                     <cell>52</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gilt.</cell>
                     <cell>53</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Patient.</cell>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Compaſſes.</cell>
                     <cell>55</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Broome.</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Cloth.</cell>
                     <cell>57</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Chirurgion.</cell>
                     <cell>58</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <pb facs="tcp:17797:38"/>Traveller</cell>
                     <cell>59</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Cipher.</cell>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Burning glaſſe.</cell>
                     <cell>61</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gloe-worme.</cell>
                     <cell>62</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Arteries.</cell>
                     <cell>63</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Marriner.</cell>
                     <cell>64</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Salt-water.</cell>
                     <cell>65</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Swimmer.</cell>
                     <cell>66</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sun.</cell>
                     <cell>67</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Servant.</cell>
                     <cell>68</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Vapour.</cell>
                     <cell>69</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Bleeding</cell>
                     <cell>70</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Scholler.</cell>
                     <cell>71</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Diall.</cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Pigeon.</cell>
                     <cell>73</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Salt.</cell>
                     <cell>74</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Tree.</cell>
                     <cell>75</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Duck.</cell>
                     <cell>76</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Marriners needle.</cell>
                     <cell>77</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Love-tokens.</cell>
                     <cell>78</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Dogge.</cell>
                     <cell>79</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Vizor.</cell>
                     <cell>80</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Ferrie-boat.</cell>
                     <cell>81</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Oven.</cell>
                     <cell>82</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Venemous creature.</cell>
                     <cell>83</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sinck.</cell>
                     <cell>84</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Kine.</cell>
                     <cell>85</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Arrowes.</cell>
                     <cell>86</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Drug.</cell>
                     <cell>87</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Potion.</cell>
                     <cell>88</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Houre-glaſſe.</cell>
                     <cell>89</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Puddle.</cell>
                     <cell>90</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Garments.</cell>
                     <cell>91</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Plowing.</cell>
                     <cell>92</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Weeds.</cell>
                     <cell>93</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>High-way.</cell>
                     <cell>94</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Shooting.</cell>
                     <cell>95</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Raine.</cell>
                     <cell>96</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Butt.</cell>
                     <cell>97</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Almanack.</cell>
                     <cell>98</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Tree.</cell>
                     <cell>99</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Breath.</cell>
                     <cell>100</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:17797:38"/>
            <head>An Alphabeticall Table of the matter to which the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſons tend.</head>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <head>A</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>Simile.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>A Boundance</hi> of outward things a hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</cell>
                     <cell>17. 18. 19, 20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Ayme</hi> of a Chriſtian.</cell>
                     <cell>36</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Afflictions</hi> their benefit.</cell>
                     <cell>41</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Afflictions</hi> why ſont.</cell>
                     <cell>58</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Gods ayme in <hi>afflictions.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>88</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Atheiſme</hi> rewarded.</cell>
                     <cell>100</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>B</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Bleſſings</hi> outward how to uſe them.</cell>
                     <cell>12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Bleſſings</hi> outward how diſpoſed</cell>
                     <cell>40</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>C</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Covetous</hi> mans curſe.</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Chriſtians</hi> carriage.</cell>
                     <cell>24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Content</hi> ſee humble.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſee ſinners.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <pb facs="tcp:17797:39"/>
                        <hi>Chriſtians</hi> and hypocrites differ,</cell>
                     <cell>53</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Civill</hi> men diſcovered.</cell>
                     <cell>62</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Conſideration</hi> beneficiall.</cell>
                     <cell>56</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Care</hi> ſee ordinances.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Cuſtome</hi> forcible.</cell>
                     <cell>80</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Conſtancie</hi> of a Chriſtian.</cell>
                     <cell>85</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Corruption</hi> diſcovered.</cell>
                     <cell>90</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Converſion</hi> of wicked men.</cell>
                     <cell>93</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>D</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Death</hi> of wicked men.</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Death</hi> of wicked men vntimely.</cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Differe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e of men after <hi>death.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>35</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Diſpoſitions</hi> different.</cell>
                     <cell>39</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Doubting</hi> with faith.</cell>
                     <cell>77</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>E</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Experience</hi> beyond knowledge.</cell>
                     <cell>54</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>F</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Fals</hi> of Gods children.</cell>
                     <cell>30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Falſe</hi> friends.</cell>
                     <cell>37</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Faith</hi> and love.</cell>
                     <cell>55</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Flight of <hi>faith.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>73</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Faith</hi> ſee doubting.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>G</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Growth</hi> after falls.</cell>
                     <cell>31</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <pb facs="tcp:17797:39"/>
                        <hi>Griefe</hi> immoderate cured.</cell>
                     <cell>70</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Grace</hi> ſanctifieth all things.</cell>
                     <cell>74</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Griefe</hi> concealed, double.</cell>
                     <cell>75</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Great</hi> men reprooved how.</cell>
                     <cell>92</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>H</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Humble</hi> men content.</cell>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Way to <hi>humilitie.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>51</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Hipocrite</hi> ſee Chriſtian.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Hipocrites</hi> behaviour.</cell>
                     <cell>78. 79</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>How to know we belong to <hi>heaven.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>83</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Hipocrite</hi> vncaſed.</cell>
                     <cell>91</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>I</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Iudgement</hi> brought by ſin.</cell>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Infirmities</hi> in the Saints.</cell>
                     <cell>27</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Infirmities</hi> to be borne with.</cell>
                     <cell>47</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Progreſſe in our ſpirituall <hi>journey.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>59</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>God <hi>immutable.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>67</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Iudgement</hi> delayed heavie.</cell>
                     <cell>96</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>K</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Vnprofitable <hi>Knowledge.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>34</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Knowledge</hi> ſee Experience.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Knowledge</hi> different in God and man.</cell>
                     <cell>98</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>L</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Life,</hi> cauſe of the ſhortneſſe of it.</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <pb facs="tcp:17797:40"/>
                        <hi>Life</hi> of good men why prolonged.</cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Love</hi> of God diſcovered,</cell>
                     <cell>44</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Love</hi> ſee faith</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Love</hi> of God efficacious.</cell>
                     <cell>61</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Labour</hi> loſt,</cell>
                     <cell>66</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>M</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mercy</hi> in God by nature.</cell>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mercy</hi> in God ſupreame,</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Men</hi> different.</cell>
                     <cell>49</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Meanes</hi> how to vſe them.</cell>
                     <cell>64</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Meanes</hi> ſee ſpirit.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>To ſerve God in ſerving <hi>men,</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>68</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Different carriage in an evill <hi>man.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>81</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Miracles</hi> ceaſed.</cell>
                     <cell>99</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>O</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Outward</hi> things variable.</cell>
                     <cell>38</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Care in Gods <hi>ordinances.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>71</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Obduration</hi> finall.</cell>
                     <cell>75</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>P</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Promiſes</hi> the uſe of them,</cell>
                     <cell>9</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Plenty</hi> enjoyed by wicked men.</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Puniſhments.</cell>
                     <cell>21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Puniſhment</hi> feared by wicked men.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Purpoſe</hi> of God effected.</cell>
                     <cell>4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Perſecutors</hi> their end.</cell>
                     <cell>50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Prayers</hi> how to regard them.</cell>
                     <cell>86</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Prayers</hi> long ſometimes dangerous.</cell>
                     <cell>97</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17797:40"/>
                  <head>R</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Reaſon</hi> the defect of it.</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Rewards</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Riches</hi> vncertaine.</cell>
                     <cell>33</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>S</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Secret</hi> ſins dangerous.</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sin</hi> willbe felt at laſt.</cell>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sins</hi> of others why not offenſive.</cell>
                     <cell>5</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sin</hi> the deformity of it.</cell>
                     <cell>25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sin</hi> the nature of it.</cell>
                     <cell>28</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>God our <hi>ſtrength.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>29</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Strength</hi> from Chriſt,</cell>
                     <cell>32</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Scriptures</hi> how vnderſtood.</cell>
                     <cell>42</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sinceritie</hi> the reward of it.</cell>
                     <cell>43</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sinners</hi> how brought to Chriſt.</cell>
                     <cell>46</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Soule</hi> the object of it.</cell>
                     <cell>60</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Meanes effectuall by the <hi>Spirit.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>63</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Not to hoard up for our <hi>ſelves.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>69</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Effiicacie of the <hi>Spirit.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>87</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>T</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Thankfulneſſe</hi> the way to it.</cell>
                     <cell>45</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Trouble</hi> the cauſe of it.</cell>
                     <cell>57</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Tranſcient</hi> things how to ſee them.</cell>
                     <cell>72</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Time</hi> of God the beſt.</cell>
                     <cell>89</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <pb facs="tcp:17797:41"/>
                  <head>V</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Variable</hi> ſee outward.</cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <table>
                  <head>W</head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Weake</hi> how to inſtruct them,</cell>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Weakeneſſe</hi> of man,</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Wickedneſſe</hi> diſcovered.</cell>
                     <cell>52</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Worldly</hi> things the nature of them.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Worldly</hi> things defective.</cell>
                     <cell>76</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>World</hi> the older the worſe.</cell>
                     <cell>84</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Way</hi> of God to be kept in.</cell>
                     <cell>94</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:17797:41"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
